{
    "questions": [
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the National Manufacturing Policy-2011 (NMP-2011): 1. It aimed to increase the sectoral share of manufacturing in India's GDP to at least 25%. 2. NMP-2011 sought to enhance global competitiveness and domestic value addition in the Indian manufacturing sector. 3. Niti Aayog is responsible for the coordination between the central and state governments for the development of National Investment & Manufacturing Zones. Which of the statements given above is/are correct?",
        "options": [
          "a. Only 1 and 2",
          "b. Only 1 and 3",
          "c. Only 2 and 3",
          "d. 1, 2, and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "a"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is/are true regarding the National Industrial Corridor Programme (NICP)? 1. The Asian Development Bank (ADB) is a financial partner in India’s National Industrial Corridor Development Program (NICDP). 2. Projects under the National Industrial Corridor Programme are integrated into the National Infrastructure Pipeline. 3. The NICP involves the development of smart cities to attract manufacturers and investors.",
        "options": [
          "a. Only 1",
          "b. Only 2",
          "c. Only 1 and 2",
          "d. 1, 2, and 3"
        ],
        "answer": "d"
      },
      {
        "question": "The Make in India 2.0 initiative by the Government of India is coordinated by which of the following departments for the manufacturing and service sectors respectively?",
        "options": [
          "a. Department of Commerce and Department for Promotion of Industry and Internal Trade (DPIIT)",
          "b. Ministry of Finance and Ministry of Commerce",
          "c. Department for Promotion of Industry and Internal Trade (DPIIT) and Department of Commerce",
          "d. Niti Aayog and DPIIT"
        ],
        "answer": "c"
      },
      {
        "question": "Regarding the share of the manufacturing sector in India's GDP, which of the following statements is correct based on the information provided?",
        "options": [
          "a. It is approximately one-third, similar to China's manufacturing share in its GDP.",
          "b. India aims to achieve a nearly 13% growth rate in the manufacturing sector to significantly increase its GDP contribution.",
          "c. Its contribution is around 15-17%, which is considered below its potential compared to other Asian countries.",
          "d. India has already achieved its target of a 25% share of manufacturing in GDP by 2025."
        ],
        "answer": "c"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following is not explicitly mentioned as one of the four pillars of the 'Make in India' initiative?",
        "options": [
          "a. New Processes",
          "b. New Infrastructure",
          "c. New Sectors",
          "d. New Technology"
        ],
        "answer": "d"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following are potential impacts of the 'Make in India' initiative? 1. Reduce red-tapism 2. Make Indian industries more competitive 3. Construct infrastructure in India 4. Promote Micro, Small, and Medium Enterprises (MSMEs)",
        "options": [
          "a. Only 1 and 2",
          "b. Only 2 and 3",
          "c. Only 1, 2, and 3",
          "d. 1, 2, 3, and 4"
        ],
        "answer": "d"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct regarding the 'Make in India' initiative? 1. It aims to promote skill-based employment in the manufacturing sector. 2. The initiative slowed down significantly post-COVID-19 mainly due to inflation.",
        "options": [
          "a. Only 1",
          "b. Only 2",
          "c. Both 1 and 2",
          "d. None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "a"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider the following statements regarding the Production Linked Incentive (PLI) Scheme: 1. Subsidies are provided based on incremental sales and investment in plant and machinery. 2. Incentives are disbursed only after production has commenced in India. 3. It aims to foster the growth of global champion companies in various sectors. 4. The PLI scheme currently covers 13 sectors.",
        "options": [
          "a. Only 1, 2, and 3",
          "b. Only 2, 3, and 4",
          "c. Only 1, 3, and 4",
          "d. 1, 2, 3, and 4"
        ],
        "answer": "d"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is/are correct about the sectors covered under the Production Linked Incentive (PLI) Scheme? 1. The PLI scheme currently includes 14 sectors. 2. The drone sector is one of the latest sectors to be included under the PLI scheme.",
        "options": [
          "a. Only 1",
          "b. Only 2",
          "c. Both 1 and 2",
          "d. None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "c"
      },
      {
        "question": "The industrial sector's dependence on the agricultural sector includes:",
        "options": [
          "a. The provision of food and other consumption goods for industrial sector employees.",
          "b. The supply of raw materials for agro-based industries.",
          "c. The agricultural sector serving as a market for industrial products.",
          "d. All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "d"
      },
      {
        "question": "What was one of the primary targets of the 'Make in India' program concerning the manufacturing sector's growth rate?",
        "options": [
          "a. To achieve a consistent growth rate of 10% per annum.",
          "b. To increase the manufacturing sector’s growth rate to 12-14% per annum.",
          "c. To double the growth rate of the manufacturing sector within three years.",
          "d. To maintain the existing growth rate while focusing on job creation."
        ],
        "answer": "b"
      },
      {
        "question": "What was the intended contribution of the manufacturing sector to India's GDP by the year 2025 under the 'Make in India' vision?",
        "options": [
          "a. 20%",
          "b. 25%",
          "c. 30%",
          "d. 35%"
        ],
        "answer": "b"
      },
      {
        "question": "The Phased Manufacturing Programme (PMP) primarily aimed to:",
        "options": [
          "a. Boost exports of manufactured goods from India.",
          "b. Attract foreign direct investment in high-technology manufacturing.",
          "c. Increase the share of locally-procured components in Indian manufacturing.",
          "d. Provide financial incentives for large-scale manufacturing units."
        ],
        "answer": "c"
      },
      {
        "question": "In its initial phase, the Production Linked Incentive (PLI) scheme was particularly focused on:",
        "options": [
          "a. Automotive manufacturing",
          "b. Pharmaceutical production",
          "c. Mobile handset assembly",
          "d. Renewable energy equipment manufacturing"
        ],
        "answer": "c"
      },
      {
        "question": "Which of the following could be a criterion for a Non-MSME business to be eligible under the Production Linked Incentive (PLI) scheme?",
        "options": [
          "a. A minimum threshold of exports achieved in the previous financial year.",
          "b. The achievement of a minimum threshold of incremental investment and incremental sales of manufactured goods, with a minimum investment of Rs 100 crores.",
          "c. Having a certain percentage of foreign equity.",
          "d. Being located in a designated industrial zone."
        ],
        "answer": "b"
      }
    ]
  }